Bhaskar Sinha

Orcid id:0000-0001-6228-4406 52/2446, Bandra (E), Mumbai, Maharastra - 400051, India prof.b.sinha@gmail.com +91 - 7045641699

Profile

Dynamic and accomplished professional, with over twelve years of academic and analytical experience. Reputed for effective team management skills and successful product line management in progressively challenging management roles, as well as outstanding analytical knowledge with demonstrated capability to interpret, summarize, and forecast data for meaningful application. An experienced management researcher with a rich understanding of financial modeling, mergers and acquisitions, valuations, and industry analysis for supporting business development and marketing strategy.

Specialties: Strong analytical and data handling skills, flair for numbers, keen interest in business research, firm financing decisions, investment banking, and private equity space.

Technical Skills

- R, STATA, Eviews MATLAB, SPSS, and C
- Financial and Economic Modelling (Time Series, VAR and LPM)

Education

Gokhale Institute of Politics and Economics, Pune, India

August 2022 - August 2024 Cumulative GPA: 7.25/10.00Master of Science in Economics[PSHE]

Thesis Title: Impacts of Neighborhoods on Inter-Generational Mobility Exposure in India

Management Training Program, ICFAI University, Hyderabad, India

2004-2007

Major: Finance

PGDM: Major: Finance

Cumulative GPA:9.5/10.00

Kirloskar Institute for Advanced Management Studies, Harihar, India

2000 - 2002Cumulative GPA: 3.14/4.00

Nagpur University, Nagpur, India

1995 - 1999

Bachelor of Engineering: Major: Electronics

Percentage: 76.48

Academic Appointments

RIMSR, University of Mumbai

Mumbai, India

Assistant Professor: Finance

2015 - Present (on study leave)

- Taught Valuation and Portfolio Management at the Master's level.
- Taught project finance section for final semester Master's candidates.

ICFAI Business School (IBS)

Hyderabad, India

Assistant Professor: Finance

2006 - 2012

- Taught: Security Analysis and Portfolio Management.
- Core member of the Faculty Recruitment Committee (Finance).

Professional Appointments

IDBI Bank Ltd. Lucknow, India

Executive (Operations)

2002 - 2004

• Profile: Liasoning with HNI clients, branch banking sales, and credit allocation.

• Major Accomplishment: improved customer retention by 35% (Quarterly) and NIM by 4%(YoY).

Videocon International Ltd.

Pune, India

Management Trainee

April-Dec,2002

- Profile: Implement marketing strategy and programs for two product lines Refrigerators and Washing Machines- to improve revenue.
- Major Accomplishment: focussed sales drive for seasonal customers (for example Ganesh Chaturthi,10th September 2002) which improved gross profit by 9% (third Qtr.).

Projects

- Mapping Out the Demographic Diversities in the Contexts of Castes and Regions in India 2024
- Feasibility Study regarding setting up a material testing lab in India G.M., Michigan, US 2001
- Towards Convergence HCL Infosystems Ltd., Bangalore 2001
- Meteorology testing lab software development

TATA Steel, Jamshedpur 1997

Conferences and Workshops

- Contemporary Issues in Demography & Development in India, XXI Bhopal Seminar 2023
- Paper presented at International Conference XXI Bhopal Seminar 2023
- Workshop conducted "Advanced Business Analytics using R" CIMR, Mumbai 2019
- Paper selected in International Conference on Finance & Applied Economics GIPE 2019
- Participant : Winter School Delhi School of Economics 2018
- Paper presented ML and Individual Behaviour at International Conferences on Marketing Challenges in Emerging Markets
- Participant:4th International Workshop on Quantitative Finance IDRBT, IGIDR, IIT Kanpur, RPI USA 2012
- 1st Indian Financial System Conference Wharton Business School (UPenn) 2007
- Paper presented at 9th Capital Markets Conference Indian Institute of Capital Markets 2006
- Book chapter in "Marketing Research" Tata McGraw Hill 2002

Grants & Fellowships

- Fee waiver (50 percent) by Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, GoI to pursue a Health Economics major in Post Graduation 2023-2024
- Full Scholarship from ICFAI University for the Visiting Scholars Program at Martin J. Whitman School of Management, Syracuse University (NY)

 2005-2007

Achievements

- Received Dean's Letter of Recommendation to pursue research on Inflation Targeting along with PhD candidates for a summer internship at IGIDR, Mumbai 2023-2024
- Case Study Competition winner at TAPMI, Manipal
- Best Research Paper in National Conference "Dimensions in Research" 2015
- Paper accepted at 7th NTU IEFA Conference, Taiwan 2007
- Awarded highest grade for the final-term paper presentation GIPE, Pune 2024

Volunteering

Associated with Sri Ramakrishna Vivekananda Sevashram, Kurumgram philanthropically which provides education and vocational training for underprivileged children at the village level. Proud recipient of a letter of appreciation for my contribution to this important cause.